Hopi Traditionalist Movement papers, 1949-1972
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Hopi Traditionalist Movement papers, 1949-1972
AZ 374
This collection consists of correspondence, transcripts of meetings, clippings, legal papers, and printed material published by members of the movement.
Hopi Traditionalists
.4 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
This movement opposed policies of Hopi Tribal Council, Peabody Coal Company, Indian Claims Commission, and others which threatened traditional Hopi land and life.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of correspondence, transcripts of meetings, clippings, legal papers, and printed material published by members of the movement.
Access Terms
Peabody Coal Company
Hopi Indians -- Social life and customs
Hopi Indians -- Government relations
Hopi Indians -- Land tenure
Coal mines and mining -- Arizona -- Black Mesa (Navajo County and Apache County)
Strip mining -- Environmental aspects -- Southwest, New
Black Mesa (Navajo County and Apache County, Ariz.)
Correspondence
Container List
- Inventory. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letters and statements. 1949-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letters and statements. 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Black Mesa Controversy. 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Black Mesa Controversy: Peabody Coal Company, Drilling and Exploration Permit. November 28, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Black Mesa Controversy: Peabody Coal Company, "Mining Coal on Black Mesa." 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Black Mesa Controversy: Environmentalists' Statements. 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Black Mesa Controversy: [Hopi Traditionalists] Plaintiffs vs. Roger C. B. Morton and Peabody Coal Company, Defendants. 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Statements of Hopi Traditionalist Leaders. 1957-1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes The Great Resistance, A Hopi Anthology, George Yamada, ed., 1957.
- Statements of Hopi Progressives. 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Hippie Controversy. 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Historic documents and letters reprinted for the Hopi Traditionalist Movement. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Papers regarding the Hopi Traditionalist Movement. 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Includes:
  "Political Socialization of the Hopi 'Traditional' Faction," by Shuichi Nagata, 1968
  "The Fed-Up Hopi: Resistance of the American Indian and the Silence of the Good Anthropologists," by Richard O. Clemmer, 1969
  "Economic Development vs. Aboriginal Land Use: An Attempt to Predict Culture Change on an Indian Reservation in Arizona," by Richard O. Clemmer, 1970.